Vic Herman Papers
Vic Herman Papers
1943-1974
Herman, Vic, 1919-1999.
6.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American illustrator, painter, and commercial artist. Collection includes correspondence, clippings and articles about Herman, and original and published artwork. The bulk of the collection consists of commercial work done for the 7-Up company.
149048
Biographical History
Vic Herman (1919-1999) was an American cartoonist and illustrator. He worked primarily in corporate art, and created many familiar characters such as Winnie the Wac (U.S. Navy), Elsie the Cow (Borden), Reddy Kilowatt (electricity generation industry), 7-UP Sam (7-Up), Lernda Lesson, Roscoe, Al Vann, Keg and Case, Sad Shad (Johnson & Johnson), Mike Master, Two Dollar Joe, Will Selmore, Hy Proof, Mr Magic Motion Mojud Man, The Phillips 66 man, and Bert Brew. He also illustrated and wrote books for elementary public school children and taught at schools in California and at New York University.
Herman began to develop a love for Mexico when he attended Mexican-American elementary schools as a child in California, and when he returned to painting later in his career, some of his work focused on Mexico and Mexican themes. His paintings created a cultural bridge between Mexico and the United States, since both governments individually sponsored his work, and he was known as the "Norman Rockwell of Mexico" and "Ambassador With A Brush." Other high points of his career included covering Mexico for Gourmet magazine, being given a gallery to display his works in Los Angeles from the Mexican government, and being the only American or Mexican to sketch the dances of the Ballet Folklorico de Mexico while on tour.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Vic Herman Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, original art and printed material. The bulk of the collection consists of commercial work done for the 7-Up company.
Correspondence contains a small number of letters to Herman from various individuals. A few items relate to Herman's 1973 "Faces of Mexico" exhibit.
Memorabilia includes several articles about Herman and a variety of articles, clippings, advertisements and other material relating to Herman's 1973 "Faces of Mexico" exhibit.
Original art contains paste-ups, sketches, and photocopied proof pages for work Herman did for 7-Up, as well as magazine cartoons and illustrations, some original Winne the WAC cartoons, and miscellaneous sketches and color work.
Printed material contains final printed version of some of the 7-Up publications and a few magazine illustrations.
Arrangement of the Collection
All material is arranged alphabetically by type and then by title; within each title items are arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
My Days Are Made of Butterflies by Sano M. Galea'i Fa'apouli, illustrated by Vic Herman, transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Herman, Vic, 1919-1999.; Winnie the WAC.; Seven-Up Company.; United States. -- Army. -- Women's Army Corps.; United States. -- Army -- Military life.; Stars and stripes (Newspaper); Pardon my sex, doctor.; Advertising.; Commercial art.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Physicians -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nurses -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Illustrators -- United States.; Mexico -- Pictorial works.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Sketches.; Illustrations.; Photographs.; Publicity.; Artists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1968-1974; includes some related to "Faces of Mexico" (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1946; 1960,; 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - "Many Faces of Mexico" exhibit, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - National Cartoonists' Society Salute to World War II Cartoonists, 1965; includes photographs, article in The 7-Up Leader (Box 1)
  - PR/marketing material, Vic Herman Productions brochures, sample art, testimonials from clients, etc. (Box 1)
  - Sketch of Herman by Bernard D'Andrea, photoreproduction (Box 1)
  - Winnie the WAC material, 1965; includes photographs, newspaper clippings, layout for article on illustration board (Box 1)
- Original art
  - 7-Up
    - Progressive Sales Manual
      - Paste-ups, pages 1-71 (Oversize 1)
      - Paste-ups, pages 72-146 (Oversize 2)
    - Sales Maker's Idea Book
      - Paste-ups, 1969, Nov, Dec (Oversize 3)
      - Paste-ups, 1970, Mar, Aug-Dec (Oversize 3)
      - Proofs and typescript, 1970, Mar, Aug-Dec (Box 1)
      - Paste-ups, 1971, Jan-Feb (Oversize 3)
      - Proofs and typescript, 1971, Jan-Feb (Box 1)
      - Paste-ups, 1971, Mar-Jul, Dec (Oversize 4)
      - Proofs and typescript, 1971, Mar-Jul, Dec (Box 1)
      - Paste-ups, 1972, Jan-Feb, May-Dec (Oversize 5)
      - Proofs and typescript, 1972, Jan-Feb, May-Sep; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Proofs and typescript, 1972, Oct-Dec (Box 2)
      - Paste-ups, Undated (Oversize 5)
    - Selling, Advertising and Merchandising with 7-Up SAM
      - Paste-ups, 1965 Jul, Sep-Dec (Oversize 6)
      - Paste-ups, 1966 Jan-Feb, Apr-Dec (Oversize 7)
      - Paste-ups, 1967 Jan-Sep, Nov-Dec (Oversize 8)
      - Paste-ups, 1968, Jan, Feb, Mar, May, Jun (Oversize 9)
  - Magazine work
    - Magazine cartoons, 1943-1947 (Oversize 10)
    - Magazine illustrations, 1940-1960 (Oversize 10)
  - Winnie the WAC
    - Miscellaneous cartoons, undated (Oversize 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Sketches, color work, undated (Oversize 10)
- Printed material
  - Magazine work
    - Gourmet, 1964; 1966 (Box 2)
    - In, circa 1965 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous illustrations, undated (Oversize 10)
  - Pardon my sex, doctor / Vic Herman, Farrell Publishing, circa 1955; magazine-style collection of Herman's cartoons relating to doctors, nurses, and the medical profession (Box 2)
  - 7-Up
    - Progressive Sales Manual, 1960; proofs and published volume; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Sales Maker's idea Book, 1972 Jan, Feb, Aug, Sep, Oct (Box 2)
    - Selling, Advertising and Merchandising with 7-Up SAM, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Selling, Advertising and Merchandising with 7-Up SAM, undated (Oversize 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)